(upbeat music)
- Hello, English learners.
Welcome back to English
POD, my name is Marco.
- And I'm Erica.
- And today we have a special lesson
for Arlar's sci-fi or science fiction fans.
- Yes, and actually one special user
was the inspiration for this lesson.
- Right. - So Wolfgang.
- Exactly. - This one is for you.
- Well, sci-fi is very
popular, Star Trek, Star Wars,
and well, there are some
really interesting words
that well, maybe you wouldn't use
in real life or in normal circumstances,
but you do want to understand these
movies or why they say these words, right?
- So we're gonna look at some
sci-fi language in this lesson,
but before we start, let's
look at vocabulary preview.
- Very vocabulary preview.
- And in vocabulary preview
today, we have one phrase only.
- That's right.
Unidentified spacecraft.
- Unidentified spacecraft.
- Okay, so unidentified.
- You don't know which one it is.
- You don't know the name, yeah.
You don't know the identity.
- Yes.
- Okay, and a spacecraft.
- A spacecraft is a vehicle
that travels in space.
- Okay, also known as a spaceship.
- That's right.
- Actually, this is interesting
because you know the word UFO.
- Yes.
- That comes from.
- Unidentified flying objects.
- Exactly.
- So unidentified spacecraft,
an unknown vehicle flying in space.
- Right, a UFO.
Have you ever seen a UFO?
- No.
- Oh, that's too bad.
Have you?
Of course, hasn't anyone?
- All right, well, I think the people in
our dialogue may or may not have seen a UFO.
So why don't we take a listen?
(upbeat music)
- They are breaking through,
such a blast, and it's the full power.
(upbeat music)
- Excellent, Jonathan.
- Search the ship.
She's gotta be in here somewhere.
Bring her to me.
- Lord Hater, we have a survivor here.
Where is she?
- Don't make me destroy you.
Tell me where she is.
- Not so fast.
She will no longer be your prisoner.
It's time you and I settled
this once and for all.
- You are unwise, I
think you can defeat me.
You know nothing of the
power of the obscure side.
(upbeat music)
(somber music)
- We will stop you.
- Lord Hater, we have an unidentified
spacecraft taking off from the rear dock.
They somehow managed
to escape our trigger beam.
- After them.
- They're accelerating
boards of speed of light.
We lost them, sir.
(upbeat music)
- Okay, so a really cool Lord Hater.
- I love the music and everything.
- Well, you may have noticed that
it's similar to a certain movie out there.
- I don't know, I mean,
seems quite original to me.
- But everything for educational purposes.
- That's right.
- Okay, so we saw some words
that were maybe a little bit difficult.
So let's take a look at bees
now in language takeaway.
- Language takeaway.
Well, I guess in the dialogue,
the bad guys were breaking through.
- Breaking through.
- In the simple present, it would be.
- To break through.
- Okay, break through.
And what does that mean?
- Well, let's listen to some
examples to help us find out.
- Example one.
- After 15 minutes, the
workers broke through
the wall and rescued
everyone from the fire.
- Example two.
- He is such a good player.
He broke through the entire defense.
- Example three.
- They are breaking through
our impenetrable wall.
Run.
- All right, so it's kind of like
to enter by force somewhere.
- Yeah, to maybe break some glass and
come into a room or something like that.
- Break through.
- Yeah.
- All right, so Lord
Hader had a fight with
his enemy and he said
he wants to settle this.
- To settle this.
- Settle.
So what do you do when
you settle something?
- Well, when you settle
something is you end a fight
or a dispute or an argument
or an argument or a problem.
- Yeah, when you settle an
argument, does everyone always agree?
- No, not always, right?
- Right.
- Sometimes you are forced to agree.
- Okay.
- Not everyone agrees, but
you have no other choice.
- So it's a little bit different
from reaching an agreement
because there's usually
a winner and a loser.
- Right, exactly.
Well, now another very popular word and
within sci-fi is this word tractor being.
- Traktor beam.
- A tractor beam.
Traktor beam.
- Now, I'm not sure if
this really exists in real life.
- Well, I've never heard of it.
But a tractor beam in sci-fi
movies is like this invisible
force that grabs an
object and doesn't let it
escape and brings it
towards another spaceship.
- So it's like almost like
a rope that you can't see.
- Right, and it brings it in.
So the spaceship managed
to escape their tractor beam.
- Okay, I think that
is definitely not true.
- Well, maybe, I don't know.
But in sci-fi, you will always
hear this tractor beam.
- Okay.
Now let's move on to our final word.
The spaceship was accelerating
towards the speed of light.
- Accelerating.
- To accelerate.
- That's right.
- So that means to increase speed, right?
- Yeah, just to go faster.
- To go faster.
So if you are in your car, you want to
accelerate so you can pass another car.
- Okay.
- Or even when you stop at a red light and
it turns green, - You got to accelerate.
- Okay.
- To accelerate.
- Listen to our dialogue
again and then we'll come back
and take a look at some of the
phrases that came up in this dialogue.
(upbeat music)
- They are breaking through.
Central blasters to full power.
- Excellent job.
Search the ship.
She's gotta be in here somewhere.
- Bring her to me.
- Lord Hater, we have a survivor here.
- Where is she?
Don't make me destroy you.
Tell me where she is.
- Not so fast.
She will no longer be a prisoner.
It's time you and I settled
this once and for all.
- You are unwise to
think you can defeat me.
You know nothing of the
power of the obscure side.
- We will stop you.
- Lord Hater, we have an unidentified
spacecraft taking off from the rear dock.
They somehow manage
to escape our tractor beam.
- After them, they're accelerating
towards a speed of light.
We lost them, sir.
(upbeat music)
- Well, great.
Well, great.
I think that's a little
bit more clear this time,
but like Marco said, I
wanna look at now some
phrases that you might
hear in a sci-fi context.
- Fluency Builder.
- The first phrase
that we can take a look
at, and maybe it
looks a little bit strange.
He said she will no
longer be your prisoner.
- No longer be.
So what does he mean by no longer?
- Anymore.
- Anymore, right?
- Yeah, so you will not
be my prisoner anymore.
- Okay, so how would I use
it in this form no longer be?
- You've always gotta
use it in the future tense.
- Okay.
- So she'll no longer be your prisoner.
I will no longer be your employee.
- Okay, or I can say I will
no longer be your boyfriend.
- Okay, so it's always will no longer be.
It's always in the future.
- Okay.
- One more thing Marco, is this quite
commonly used, or maybe a little bit formal?
- I think it's a little bit formal, and
it's very, to a certain point, poetic.
- Yeah, which I think is why we hear it
a little bit more often in sci-fi movies.
- All right, so no longer be.
What about our next phrase?
- You know nothing of the
power of the obscure side.
- Okay, you know nothing.
- You know nothing of.
- So again, it's very poetic.
- Yeah.
- Basically meaning you don't know about.
- You don't know about.
- Yeah.
- So again, let's take a
look at how you would use it.
- You know nothing of, and then.
- Science fiction.
- You know nothing of science fiction.
- Yeah.
- So you would use a noun afterwards.
- Exactly.
- Okay, so interesting phrases.
- Again, formal, and probably quite
often used in science fiction movies.
- But now you can understand when they use
some of these words
that maybe are a little bit
difficult, and very common
in these types of movies.
- Now let's go to our
last phrase, then this one
actually can be used in
many different circumstances.
Let's settle this once and for all.
- Okay, so we saw the verb, so
we saw the word settle already.
Now let's settle this once and for all.
- Once and for all.
- So what does that mean?
- Finally, that's right, forever.
- Okay, so once and for all, forever.
So why don't we listen to
some other examples of how
we can use this phrase once
and for all in different contexts?
- Example one, I'm fed
up with arguing about this.
Let's just settle the
argument once and for all.
- Example two.
- He claims his photographs prove
once and for all that UFOs do exist.
- Example three.
- I told him once and for all that I
don't want to be his girlfriend anymore.
- Okay, so now I think it's clear.
We've seen a lot of words.
We've seen a lot of phrases.
Let's listen to our dialogue one more time.
(upbeat music)
(dramatic music)
- They are breaking through.
Such a blast, it was the full power.
- Excellent job.
- Search the ship.
She's gotta be in here somewhere.
Bring her to me.
- Lord Hanger, we have a survivor here.
Where is she?
- Don't make me destroy you.
Tell me where she is.
- Not so fast.
She will no longer be your prisoner.
It's time you and I settled
this once and for all.
- You are unwise, I
think you can defeat me.
You know nothing of the
power of the obscure side.
(dramatic music)
- We will stop you.
- Lord Hanger, we have an unidentified
spacecraft taking off from the rear dock.
They somehow manage
to escape our trip to Bea.
- After then.
- They're accelerating
boards of speed of light.
We lost them, sir.
(upbeat music)
(dramatic music)
- Okay, so are you a big sci-fi fan?
- I think as you can tell, no, actually,
I've seen some of the Star
Wars movies but everyone
that I've watched, I've
fallen asleep in the middle of.
- Really?
- Yeah, even in the movie theater,
I fell asleep in the movie
theater watching Star Wars.
- Wow, was it too boring?
- It was too boring.
- Oh, you're not really
into the fantasy side.
- No, I just, the whole time I'm sitting
there going, "This cannot happen.
" - Well, that's why it's
called science fiction, right?
- Yes.
- But it is interesting to some people
and, well, behind Star
Wars, there is a huge culture.
Even some people know some
of the languages or symbols
that are used in it or the names of some
of the robots and models of spacecraft.
- Well, maybe we'll have to
come up with Star Wars Pives.
- Exactly.
Well, that's all for today, guys.
I hope you enjoyed our lesson.
- And, of course, if you
have questions or comments,
you can leave them in a comments
section on our website, englishpod.com.
- Well, thanks for listening, you guys.
And, until next time, goodbye.
(upbeat music)